A Guide to the Lancaster County (Va.) Judgments, 1732-1931
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Lancaster County (Va.) Judgments, 1732-1931
Library of Virginia
1133898-1134301
54 cu. ft. (121 boxes)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These items came in a transfer of court papers from Lancaster County.
Historical Information
Lancaster County was formed from Northumberland and York Counties in 1651.
The County Court was the original colonial court of adjudication and recordation, and it was the principal tribunal for the administration of local justice. The individual justices could act on small claims matters as well as criminal matters where imminent bodily harm was a possibility, there being an appeal to the full County Court, which met monthly. This court ceased to exist in 1904 and the recordation function was transferred to the circuit court.
The Superior Court of Law was created in 1808. It met twice a year in each county, presided over by a circuit-riding General Court judge. Records were filed with the County Court. It had civil and criminal jurisdiction. The court ceased to exist in 1831.
The Circuit Superior Courts of Law and Chancery, established in 1831, were the upper courts on the local level. Sessions were held twice a year in each county, presided over by a General Court judge. The counties were grouped into districts for the convenience of the judge. The court ceased to exist in 1851.
The Circuit Court was authorized by the Constitution of 1851 and established by an act of the General Assembly passed in May 1852. Courts were held twice yearly in each county, presided over by 21 judges who rode circuits in the area of their jurisdiction. The records were filed with County Court records. These courts were granted original jurisdiction concurrrent with that of the County Courts, as well as appellate jurisdiction in all civil cases of more than fifty dollars and criminal cases not "expressly cognizable in some other court," including those involving loss of life.
Scope and Content
Lancaster County (Va.) Judgments, 1732-1931, contain civil cases heard in County Court, Superior Court of Law, Circuit Superior Court, and Circuit Court in which justice was administered on the strictly formulated rules of common law. The majority of cases in this record series relate to matters of debt.
Arrangement
Chronological (Cases filed within each box by month and year they were resolved.)
Access Terms
Lancaster County (Va.) -- Circuit Court.; Lancaster County (Va.) -- Circuit Superior Court of Law and Chancery.; Lancaster County (Va.) -- County Court.; Lancaster County (Va.) -- Superior Court of Law.; Civil procedure -- Virginia -- Lancaster County.; Courts -- Virginia -- Lancaster County.; Debt -- Virginia -- Lancaster County.; Public Records -- Virginia -- Lancaster County.; Lancaster County (Va.) -- History.; Decisions -- Virginia -- Lancaster County.; Judicial records -- Virginia -- Lancaster County.; Local government records -- Virginia -- Lancaster County.
Contents List
- Judgments 1732, 1746, 1749-1751 (Barcode 1134149)
- Judgments 1751-1752 (Barcode 1134150)
- Judgments 1753-1754 (Barcode 1134151)
- Judgments 1754-1755 (Barcode 1134152)
- Judgments 1755 (Barcode 1134153)
- Judgments 1756-1757 (Barcode 1134154)
- Judgments 1757-1758 (Barcode 1134155)
- Judgments 1759-1760 (Barcode 1134156)
- Judgments 1760-1762 (Barcode 1134157)
- Judgments 1762-1763 (Barcode 1134158)
- Judgments 1764-1765 (Barcode 1134167)
- Judgments 1764 (Barcode 1134112)
- Judgments 1765-1766 (Barcode 1134174)
- Judgments 1767-1768 (Barcode 1134172)
- Judgments 1767 (Barcode 1134173)
- Judgments 1769-1770 (Barcode 1134171)
- Judgments 1770-1772 (Barcode 1134170)
- Judgments 1772-1778 (Barcode 1134159)
- Judgments 1778-1782 (Barcode 1134168)
- Judgments 1783 (Barcode 1134160)
- Judgments 1784 (Barcode 1134166)
- Judgments 1785-1786 (Barcode 1134164)
- Judgments 1785 (Barcode 1134165)
- Judgments 1787 (Barcode 1134169)
- Judgments 1787 (Barcode 1134162)
- Judgments 1787 (Barcode 1134163)
- Judgments 1787 (Barcode 1134143)
- Judgments 1788 (Barcode 1134126)
- Judgments 1788 (Barcode 1134145)
- Judgments 1788 (Barcode 1134120)
- Judgments 1789-1790 (Barcode 1134124)
- Judgments 1789 (Barcode 1134125)
- Judgments 1790-1791 (Barcode 1134123)
- Judgments 1791-1792 (Barcode 1134128)
- Judgments 1792-1793 (Barcode 1134121)
- Judgments 1793-1794 (Barcode 1134129)
- Judgments 1794-1795 (Barcode 1134119)
- Judgments 1796-1797 (Barcode 1134118)
- Judgments 1797-1798 (Barcode 1134117)
- Judgments 1798-1799 (Barcode 1134116)
- Judgments 1799 (Barcode 1134274)
- Judgments 1799-1800 (Barcode 1134275)
- Judgments 1800-1801 (Barcode 1134276)
- Judgments 1801-1802 (Barcode 1134277)
- Judgments 1802 (Barcode 1134278)
- Judgments 1802 (Barcode 1134279)
- Judgments 1803 (Barcode 1134281)
- Judgments 1803 (Barcode 1134282)
- Judgments 1803-1804 (Barcode 1134283)
- Judgments 1803 (Barcode 1134280)
- Judgments 1804 (Barcode 1134292)
- Judgments 1804 (Barcode 1134237)
- Judgments 1804-1805 (Barcode 1134051)
- Judgments 1805 (Barcode 1134297)
- Judgments 1805 (Barcode 1134298)
- Judgments 1805-1806 (Barcode 1134296)
- Judgments 1806 (Barcode 1134284)
- Judgments 1806 (Barcode 1133898)
- Judgments 1806 (Barcode 1134295)
- Judgments 1807-1808 (Barcode 1134291)
- Judgments 1807 (Barcode 1134285)
- Judgments 1809 (Barcode 1134289)
- Judgments 1809 (Barcode 1134290)
- Judgments 1810 (Barcode 1134288)
- Judgments 1810 (Barcode 1134287)
- Judgments 1811 (Barcode 1134268)
- Judgments 1812 (Barcode 1134294)
- Judgments 1813-1815 (Barcode 1134245)
- Judgments 1815-1816 (Barcode 1134270)
- Judgments 1816 (Barcode 1134251)
- Judgments 1817-1818 (Barcode 1134250)
- Judgments 1818-1819 (Barcode 1134249)
- Judgments 1819 (Barcode 1134248)
- Judgments 1820 (Barcode 1134253)
- Judgments 1820-1821 (Barcode 1134246)
- Judgments 1821-1822 (Barcode 1134254)
- Judgments 1822 (Barcode 1134244)
- Judgments 1823 (Barcode 1134243)
- Judgments 1824-1825 (Barcode 1134242)
- Judgments 1825-1826 (Barcode 1134241)
- Judgments 1826-1827 (Barcode 1134240)
- Judgments 1827-1828 (Barcode 1134175)
- Judgments 1829-1831 (Barcode 1134247)
- Judgments 1832-1833 (Barcode 1134261)
- Judgments 1833-1835 (Barcode 1134238)
- Judgments 1835-1837 (Barcode 1134267)
- Judgments 1837-1839 (Barcode 1134266)
- Judgments 1840-1841 (Barcode 1134265)
- Judgments 1841-1843 (Barcode 1134264)
- Judgments 1843-1844 (Barcode 1134252)
- Judgments 1844-1847 (Barcode 1134262)
- Judgments 1847-1850 (Barcode 1134269)
- Judgments 1851-1854 (Barcode 1134260)
- Judgments 1854-1857 (Barcode 1134259)
- Judgments 1857-1858 (Barcode 1134258)
- Judgments 1858-1860 (Barcode 1134257)
- Judgments 1861-1866 (Barcode 1134256)
- Judgments 1866-1867 (Barcode 1134255)
- Judgments 1867-1868 (Barcode 1134263)
- Judgments 1869-1870 (Barcode 1134098)
- Judgments 1871-1873 (Barcode 1134177)
- Judgments 1874-1875 (Barcode 1134084)
- Judgments 1876-1878 (Barcode 1134085)
- Judgments 1878-1880 (Barcode 1134086)
- Judgments 1881-1883 (Barcode 1134087)
- Judgments 1884-1886 (Barcode 1134088)
- Judgments 1886-1888 (Barcode 1134115)
- Judgments 1888-1890 (Barcode 1134301)
- Judgments 1891-1892 (Barcode 1134122)
- Judgments 1892-1893 (Barcode 1134136)
- Judgments 1894-1895 (Barcode 1134113)
- Judgments 1895-1897 (Barcode 1134142)
- Judgments 1897 (Barcode 1134141)
- Judgments 1898 (Barcode 1134140)
- Judgments 1899-1900 (Barcode 1134139)
- Judgments 1901-1902 (Barcode 1134127)
- Judgments 1902-1904 (Barcode 1134137)
- Judgments 1904-1908 (Barcode 1134144)
- Judgments 1908-1910 (Barcode 1134135)
- Judgments 1911-1931 (Barcode 1134134)